# Giorgos ('Yorgos') Mamakoukas

giorgosmamakoukas@u.northwestern.edu • (847) 868 - 2198 • gmamakoukas.com

#### **SUMMARY**

Mechanical Engineering/Robotics Ph.D. researcher, specializing in algorithm development, optimization methods, real-time nonlinear control, system modeling, dynamics, machine learning, and numerical methods. Extensive research, teaching, and leadership experience with a rigorous mathematical background, first-author publications in top-tier peer-reviewed journals and conferences in robotics and control and hands-on experiments with robotic fish. Enthusiastic team player with an interest in the nexus of science, research, and management/business.

Keywords: nonlinear optimization and control, machine learning, algorithm development, numerical methods

## **SKILLS AND INTERESTS**

**Programming Languages:** MATLAB, Python, C, C++, Mathematica, LaTeX

Software and Toolbox: Git, Simulink, Onshape

Languages: Greek (native), English (fluent), German (advanced)

Interests: Team sports (former soccer varsity athlete), Hiking, Mentoring, Chess

## **EDUCATION**

## Northwestern University, The Graduate School, Evanston, IL

Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering | GPA: 3.93/4.0

Expected June 2020

Master of Science in Mechanical Engineering | GPA: 3.93/4.0

July 2017

Honors/Awards: Brady Scholars, Graduate Leadership and Service, Walter P. Murphy Fellowship

# Northwestern University Kellogg School of Management, Evanston, IL

Certificate in Management for Scientists and Engineers, Kellogg School of Management

Aug 2018

## Grinnell College, Grinnell, IA

Bachelor of Arts in Physics (Honors) | GPA: 3.97/4.0

May 2014

Honors/Awards: H. George Apostle Prize in Physics, Phi Beta Kappa Academic Award, George White Academic Scholarship

## **RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

Graduate Research Assistant, Interactive & Emergent Autonomy Lab, Northwestern University

Sept 2014 - Present

# Machine Learning Algorithms for Prediction and Control (2 Publications)

- Created algorithm to ensure optimal and stable data-driven system identification and improve long-horizon accuracy
- Implemented and improved real-time data-driven control of robotic systems in simulation and experiments
- Developed novel simulations to assess the effectiveness and accuracy of predicting models

# **Data-Driven Control of Robotic Fish (3 Publications)**

- Created technique to quantify and bound the model accuracy of data-driven models using Python & MATLAB
- Cleaned and analyzed data and performed error analysis to assess and improve model performance
- Employed algorithms on robotic fish for experimental tracking in disturbance using C++
- Led collaboration with Michigan State University to on-site troubleshoot and consult their experiments with robotic fish

#### Real-Time Optimal Control of Nonlinear Systems (7 Publications)

- Investigated and advanced nonlinear optimization and control algorithms
- Developed feedback algorithms using C++ software for guaranteed collision-free locomotion of robots

# Independent Research on Magnetic Levitation, California Institute of Technology, CA

June - Aug 2013

- Selected for competitive and prestigious program for magnetic isolation of gravitational wave detectors from seismic noise
- Reduced experimental setup phase from 10 weeks to 13 days by re-planning and prioritizing
- Created the solution that realized a seismic isolation technique for detecting gravitational waves

# Independent Research on Alloy Crystallography, Grinnell College, IA

June - July 2012

Pioneered experimentation with new \$220k X-ray diffractometer to discover new crystals

• Discovered new crystals and analyzed their atomic structure

#### SELECTED LEADERSHIP AND SERVICE EXPERIENCE

# Brady Scholar Fellow, Northwestern University

June 2016 - June 2019

- Led sixteen Northwestern students to secure funding and perform energy audits for affordable housing
- Managed three grants (\$2k), training of 21 participants, and completion of 5 energy audits in Evanston apartments
- Conducted weekly meetings, coordinated tasks, and evaluated their progress

## Presenter at Museum of Science and Industry Annual Robot Block Party

Apr 2015 - Apr 2019

Presented and communicated complex robotics research projects to hundreds of adults and children

## President of Mechanical Engineering Graduate Student Society, Northwestern University

Sept 2016 - Feb 2018

- Expanded the program by creating new positions and establishing annual social and career development events
- Streamlined communication and outreach processes by creating a website and a contact e-mail address

## Supervisor of Teaching Assistants, Grinnell College

Aug 2013 - May 2014

- Promoted to an inaugural role to assess and guide all 10+ science TAs to improve teaching and communication skills
- Oversaw and filmed TAs for 5 hours/week during their teaching and advised them on their strengths and weaknesses

## **SELECTED MENTORSHIP AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

## Robotics Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University

Sept 2016 - Dec 2016

• Received 97.8% positive evaluation from 73 students

# Physics and Math Mentor, Grinnell College

Aug 2011 - May 2014

Identified and bridged knowledge gaps and motivated students both in 25+ student classes and in 1-on-1 tutoring

## Modern Greek Instructor, Grinnell College

Aug 2011 – May 2012

- Collaborated with another student to design curriculum and teach a new credit-bearing college course
- Participated in seminars on effective communication styles and teaching methods

## **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS (5 of 12)**

- **G. Mamakoukas,** M. Castano, X. Tan and T. D. Murphey, 'Online data-driven control of robotic systems using derivative-based Koopman operators', in *Transactions on Robotics*. Submitted 2020.
- **G. Mamakoukas**, M. Castano, X. Tan and T. D. Murphey, '<u>Local Koopman operators for data-driven control of robotic systems</u>', in *Robotics: Science and Systems*, 2019.
- **G. Mamakoukas**, M. A. MacIver, and T. D. Murphey, 'Feedback synthesis for underactuated systems using sequential second-order needle variations', in *International Journal of Robotics Research*, 2018. [Invited as best conference paper]
- **G. Mamakoukas,** M. A. MacIver, and T. D. Murphey, 'Superlinear convergence using controls based on second-order needle variations', in *Conference on Decision and Control*, 2018.
- **G. Mamakoukas**, M. A. MacIver, and T. D. Murphey, 'Feedback synthesis for controllable underactuated systems using sequential second-order actions', in *Robotics: Science and Systems*, 2017.